<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miracles vnmasked A treatise prouing that miracles are not infallible signes of the true and orthodoxe faith: that popish miracles are either counterfeit or diuellish. Euidently confirmed by authorities of holy Scripture, of antient doctors, of graue and learned Spanish authors, by weighty reasons, manifest examples, and most true histories which haue happened in Spaine, and appeare in bookes there printed. By Ferdinando Texeda, Batchelar in Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Tejeda, Fernando de, fl. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118363</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18960</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18960)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1498:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miracles vnmasked A treatise prouing that miracles are not infallible signes of the true and orthodoxe faith: that popish miracles are either counterfeit or diuellish. Euidently confirmed by authorities of holy Scripture, of antient doctors, of graue and learned Spanish authors, by weighty reasons, manifest examples, and most true histories which haue happened in Spaine, and appeare in bookes there printed. By Ferdinando Texeda, Batchelar in Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Tejeda, Fernando de, fl. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Edward Blackamore, and are to be sould at his shop at the south doore of Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Tejeda, of a Spanish work of his (STC).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliography.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Miracles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18960:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18960:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Miracles vnmasked. A TREATISE Prouing that MIRACLES are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſignes of the true and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe FAITH: That POPISH MIRACLES are either coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit or diuelliſh. Euidently confirmed by authorities of holy Scripture, of antient Doctors, of graue and learned <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Authors, by weighty reaſons, manifeſt examples, and moſt <hi>true Hiſtories which haue happened in</hi> Spaine, and appeare in Bookes there Printed. By FERDINANDO TEXEDA, Batchelar in Diuinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for EDWARD BLACKAMORE, and are to be ſould at his ſhop at the South doore of <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18960:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18960:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, IOHN EGERTON, Lord ELSMERE, Earle of <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall TREATISE which I compoſed in my owne language, I now ſet forth in the Engliſh tongue; vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereunto by the importunate entreaty of ſome friends of mine, who perſwaded mee that it would be no leſſe for the good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of faithfull Chriſtians, then the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them which are not ſo. The many benefits, and charitable fauours which I haue receiued at your Lordſhips liberall hands, ſeeme to call vpon mee, and tell mee that I ought (to cumply in part with the ſtrict obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation wherein I ſtand bound to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to dedicate the ſame to your Noble ſelfe: hoping that the ſame reaſon by which I offer this ſmall manifeſtation of my grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:18960:3"/>heart to your honourable protection, will be a ſufficient motiue to your Lordſhip to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, and giue it a fauourable aſpect: For where a Noble minde hath once conferred benefits, thoſe benefits may lawfully be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as ſeales to an obligation of future fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Since the ſacrifice which Ieſus Chriſt made of his precious bloud for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is acknowledged by his diuine Maieſtie as a moſt powerfull inducement whereby we may expect euery day new bleſſings from the ſame fountaine. And I haue a moſt ſtrong hope that your Lordſhip will not reiect this piece of ſeruice, becauſe ſmall in reſpect of your greatneſſe; for your breaſt is Princely, <hi>Et non minus eſt regium, atque adeo humanum paruula accipere, quam largiri magna;</hi> And your Lordſhips gracious acceptance hereof will impoſe a new bond vpon me, to pray the Almighty to enrich your Noble ſoule with continuall infuſions of diuine graces, and to powre down on your honourable eſtate and family, hourely ſhowres of tranſitory bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips deuoted in all humble duty, <hi>FERDINANDO TEXEDA.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authorities">
            <pb facs="tcp:18960:3"/>
            <head>The Bookes out of which this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is gathered, are theſe following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Bras del Maeſtro gracian, impreſſas en Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid. Anno <hi>1619.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Coronica y hiſtoria de la fundacion y pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſo de la prouincia de Caſtilla del Orden de ſan Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, &amp;c. por el P. Salazar. En Madrid. Anno <hi>1612.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Hiſtoria y Anal relacion de las coſas que hizieron los padres de la Compannia de Ieſus, por las partes de Oriente, &amp;c. Por el Doctor Figueroa. En Madrid. Anno <hi>1614.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Sermones de Payua. En Madrid. Anno <hi>1617.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Diſcurſos para todos los Euangelios de la Quareſma por el P. Maeſtro Fonſeea. En Madrid. Anno <hi>1614.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Teſoro de la lengua Caſtellana, o Eſpannola, por el licenciado Couarruuias. En Madrid. Anno <hi>1611.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Deſenganno de Sierra. En Madrid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Prado eſpiritual por el doctor Sanctoro. En Vallado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid. Anno <hi>1614.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relacion de la ſantidad y llagas de la Madre Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria de la viſitacion, Priora que fue de la Annunciada de Lisboa, y lo que fue declarado en la ſentencia que ſedio. En Seuilla. Anno <hi>1589.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Hiſtoria de ſan Antonio de Padua por Mateo Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. En Seuilla Anno <hi>1605.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Tratados de Soſa. En Salamanca. Anno <hi>1623.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Venida de Chriſto por el P. ojea. En Medina del Campo. Anno <hi>1602.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18960:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Hiſtoria de la ſagrada Orden de predicadores. En los remotes Reynos de la Etiopia por el P. Vrreta. En va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia. Anno <hi>1611.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Tomo <hi>2.</hi> de la Monarchia de Pineda. En Barcelona. Anno <hi>1620.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> Philoſophia moral de Eccleſiaſticos por el Maeſtro Torreſ. En Barcelona. Anno <hi>1621.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> Quarto tomo de la perfecion, por el P. Puente. En Pamplona Anno <hi>1616.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Hiſtoria del gran Reyno de la China por el Maeſtro Nendoza. En Anucres. Anno <hi>1596.</hi> Con priuilegio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> Iſagoge in totam ſacram Scripturam, Autore Lude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice de tena Epiſcopo Dertuſenſi. En Hueſca, Anno <hi>1622.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="prologue">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18960:4"/>
               <head>The PROLOGVE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue Religion and Faith is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great conſequence, that who ſo profeſſeth it not, cannot enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: For (as the Apoſtle teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) <hi>wee are ſaued by faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> The firſt part whereof is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and acceptation of ſound Doctrine; according to which,<note place="margin">Damaſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de orthod. fid. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Damaſcen</hi> learnedly concludeth, <hi>that it is impoſsible to bee ſaued without Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore we ought with great ſtudy, care, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, to procure, imbrace, and hold firmely the true Orthodox and Apoſtolicall Religion, ſeeing without it we cannot hope for any thing but condemnation and death.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing in theſe our daies there are ſo many and diuers Religions, it is requiſite wee ſhould vſe a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and iudicious examination, that none may be ſo hardy as to preferte vnto vs, droſſe in ſtead of Gold, nor we to admit and lay hold of Hereſie in ſtead of truth, and ſo vndergoe a diſaſtrous ſhipwracke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation: ſo Chriſt the principall Paſtor of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18960:5"/>Church, counſelled, taught, and charged vs; ſaying, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe in this Scruteney, ſeldome times wee encounter aright, but often times we faile; it is moſt important, and abſolutely neceſſary, to learne and obſerue ſome meanes by which wee may infallibly diſtinguiſh that which is precious, from that which is baſe, and the truth from falſhood: For as there is a touch-ſtone to try Mettals by, ſo it is fit wee ſhould haue ſome meaſure and ſquare by which we may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe and rule Faith and Doctrine.</p>
               <p>This Rule and Square of Faith, we Proteſtants af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to bee the ſacred Scripture comprized in the Bookes of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, &amp; this is euident by many places of the ſaid Scripture, as many of our Doctors haue proued very perſpicuouſly, to whom I referre my ſelfe, being content for this preſent to confirme this doctrine with the authority which is of no ſmall account, eſpecially amongſt vs <hi>Spaniards</hi> of the learned Doctor,<note place="margin">Tena in Iſag. in tot. ſacr. ſcript. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocatur Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ab Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, quia probatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrna inſtructio eſt de nulla falſitate ſuſpecta; quare, &amp; Canon, vei Regula dicitur, quoniam ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, vtlydium lapiden ſum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doi dogmata ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminande.</note> 
                  <hi>Tena</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tortoſa:</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth the Scripture an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> becauſe it is a moſt approued inſtruction, and ſuſpected of no falſhood, therefore it is called alſo a <hi>Canon</hi> or <hi>Rule,</hi> becauſe points of Faith are to be examined by it as by a Touch-ſtone: The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is of a farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent opinion from <hi>Tortoſa;</hi> for he caſting Scripture aſide, becauſe it manifeſtly conuinceth his Doctrine, propoundeth ſome exteriour ſignes and markes, by which hee would haue vs to iudge of and diſcerne true Religion and Chriſtian Faith; theſe are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of the ſucceſſion of Ecclefiaſticall Miniſters, Monaſticall Sanctity, Miracles, and other ſuch like,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18960:5"/>which are fitter to obtenebrate, then to enlighten the eyes of the vnderſtanding in the way of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>My ſcope and purpoſe is, to make it obuious and plaine to the eyes of all who ſhut them not as Moles, that they may not ſee, the incertainty and vanity of theſe ſignes which the Papiſts doe ſo highly eſteeme; but in this Treatiſe I will onely ſpeake of that which concerneth Miracles, reſeruing the remainder for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſes, which God willing I will in fit time print.</p>
               <p>And becauſe euery kinde of Doctrine hath it's va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity from the authority of him that teacheth it, or from reaſon, that euinceth it, or from thoſe Authors which vphold it; though there bee wanting ſufficient authority vnto my perſon, yet I will endeauour to verifie what I haue here ſaid, by ſuch Doctors as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be reiected in regard of the authenticke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation they hold amongſt thoſe of my Nation, for whoſe benefit and good I haue vndertaken this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and am ready to imploy that ſmall Talent which God hath giuen vnto me, for the ſaluation of their ſoules; yea, if need ſo required, to lay downe my owne life for them: I beſeech the diuine Maieſty to bleſſe this my ſmall worke, that the faithfull may gaine profit and benefit by it, and that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the glory of his moſt holy name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18960:6"/>
               <head>That we cannot, nor ought to iudge of Religion onely by Miracles.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee deny not but that true Miracles are the ſeales and teſtimonials of Euangelicall Faith, but we diſtinguiſh betweene Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith when it was to be propagated, &amp; now that it is propagated: when it was to be propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated amongſt the Gentiles, Chriſt indued his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with the gift of Miracles, becauſe as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>at that time Faith was a ſcandal to the Iewes, &amp; folly to the Gentiles;</hi> and therfore it was greatly countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Miracles, which increaſed the number of the faithfull; but now they are not neceſſary, becauſe Faith is already greatly defuſed throughout the world, and ſufficiently fortified by the miracles of the firſt ages, ſo that now it is not ſare, but rather very dangerous to iudge of Religion meerely by Miracles.</p>
               <p>And that this may clearely appeare, wee muſt firſt obſerue, that Miracles are not the perpetuall compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of true and Catholike Doctrine; according to the Aſſertion of the learned Father <hi>Puente,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Puente <hi>4.</hi> tomo de la perfecion pag. <hi>619.</hi>
                  </note> in theſe words: <hi>The Doctors and Preachers cannot ordinarily authorize their perſons, nor the Doctrine they teach by Miracles, becauſe they are not now behoofefull amongſt Chriſtians, neither haue all power to doe them:</hi> of the fame opinion is Doctor <hi>Fonſeca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fonſeca enſus diſcurſos. pag. <hi>220.</hi>
                  </note> and prooueth it by three reaſons: the firſt, becauſe many were and are conuerted without them; the ſecond wee mentioned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18960:6"/>formerly; to wit, that the Primitiue Church being in it's minority, had need of Miracles, which the Church now being in it's full growth requireth not; the third is, becauſe where holy Scripture is, there is no need of Miracles. All which my Author proueth by teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Scripture:<note place="margin">Torres enſu Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophia. Pag. <hi>155.</hi> Chriſoft. in ca. <hi>13</hi> Gene. hom <hi>35.</hi> &amp; in Acta hom <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> Now conformably vnto this laſt reaſon of <hi>Fonſeca,</hi> Doctor <hi>Torres</hi> ſaith, with Saint 10. <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> that the reading of holy Writ is ſufficient to ſupply Miracles; and further, we cannot finde a meanes more conduceable vnto the end wee aime at, ſeeing that vnto the reading of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Miracles nor Signes from heauen are of no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That Miracles are alſo common to Falſe-Teachers,</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Doctrine, <hi>Fonſeca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fonſecaibid, pag. <hi>91.</hi>
                  </note> whom we formerly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, proueth by Miracles, which the Scripture foretelleth Antichriſt ſhould doe, as alſo by the example of the Witch, which the diuell cauſed to appeare in the ſhape of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and by that of the Phariſies which did caſt out diuels by vnlawfull coniurings and exorcifmes. Father <hi>Ojea</hi> ſaith with Saint <hi>Ioh. Chriſoſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ojca a Ojea haſta laoja <hi>1602</hi> del tratado de la venida de Chriſt.</note> that to caſt out diuels out of the bodies of thoſe that are poſſeſt, is common both to the Miniſters of God, and thoſe of Sathan: When thou ſeeſt any (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) that caſteth out diuels out of bodies, if he preach not truth, and worke not righteouſneſſe, ſuch a one is not a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18960:7"/>Saint, nor true Miniſter of God: But if contrarily thou ſeeſt that hee Preacheth truch and worketh righteouſneſſe; ſuch a one, though hee caſt not out diuels, hold him for a man of God and his true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and Miniſter. The ſame <hi>Oiea</hi> teſtifieth, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gentiles, there want not Miracles and prodigious ſignes; The Emperour <hi>Veſpatian</hi> being in <hi>Egypt,</hi> reſtored ſight vnto a blinde man, and to one that was lame in foot or hand, he rendred his former health and ſtrength, as is related by great Authors, whereof Father <hi>Pineda</hi> is one;<note place="margin">Pineda in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch iom <hi>2</hi> lib. <hi>11</hi> c. <hi>25. §. 2.</hi>
                  </note> and thoſe of <hi>China,</hi> which are notable Idolaters, haue amongſt infinite other, three Idols, of which they publiſh as a certaine truth, that they haue done, and daily doe many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, as <hi>Mendoza</hi> relateth; who confeſſeth that they might take effect according to their report.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the Romiſh Religion is not Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent by the glory of true and diuine Miracles.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is proued, becauſe the Miracles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo much boaſteth, branch themſelues into three kindes: the firſt containeth many fictitious Miracles which neuer hapned; the ſecond containeth ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles as hapned onely by the outward appearance: the third kinde hath an aſpect vpon ſuch prodigies as happened really and truely, but by the illuſion and Artifice of the diuell. I will handle theſe three kindes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18960:7"/>and in the firſt place, the firſt. Of this firſt kinde of fained Miracles which neuer happened, there are ſo many publiſhers in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that long ſince it cauſed a law to be ennacted in <hi>Spaine</hi> againſt them, the words wherof are theſe;<note place="margin">L <hi>10.</hi> primae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titae tit. de las Egleſias.</note> Many diſcouer or make altars in open fields, or in townes, ſaying, that in thoſe places there are ſome of the Reliques of the Saints, which as they pretend, worke Miracles, and by this meanes induce people to come from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts thither in pilgrimage,<note place="margin">Sierra en ſu de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenganno pag. <hi>209</hi>
                  </note> that ſo they might make benefit by them, &amp;c. And preſently it ſets down a way to remedy this euil: but how little benefit reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from this law, daily experience ſhoweth vs, this matter growing euery day worſe and worſe. Father <hi>Sierra</hi> lamenteth this Euill, ſaying; I am much afraid that merchandize wilbe made of deuotion; &amp; that the truth is not ſufficiently examined, becauſe ſome are intereſſed in it, the Miracles which are accounted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs of the Saints, not canonized by the Church, are not all of them certaine.<note place="margin">Primera parte de Don quixote pag. <hi>543.</hi>
                  </note> Another <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Author ſaith, that in diuine Comedies, the Authors of them doe inuent infinite falſe Miracles; and alſo in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Comedies, they attempt the doing of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which is in preiudice of the truth When a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize is vendable, euery one laboureth to imploy his ſtocke in it to inrich himſelfe. In the Romiſh Church, Miracles are very vendible, and therefore not onely Clergy-men and Fryers, but alſo Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dions traffique in them, and not onely they, but much other ſecular people, as well men as women practiſe this Merchandize; of all which,<note place="margin">Gratian en ſus Obras pag <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note> complained Doctor <hi>Gratian,</hi> ſaying, <hi>the world for our ſinnes is come to an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18960:8"/>end, for there are ſome which make benefit and gaine of ſanctity, giuing out that they haue reuelations, that ſo they may haue gifts and preſents.</hi> The ſame Author ſaith, <hi>that he met one day with a notorious theefe, whom he bad to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his euill life:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide ibid pag. <hi>94</hi>
                  </note> he anſwered, <hi>That he had about him a certaine printed prayer, which by Reuelation he knew was of ſuch efficacy, that whoſoeuer carryed it about him, could not dye without confeſsing his ſinnes, and therefore he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not for leauing his ill life. Spaine</hi> is ſo ful of ſuch and the like Prayers, often times imprinted by permiſſion of the Inquiſitors, that it drew from this Author, theſe notable words, <hi>in theſe matters of ſuperſtitious</hi> Nominas,<note place="margin">Vbiſup. Couarrubias en el teſoro de la lengua Eſpanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. Verbo Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> 
                  <hi>much harme is done amongſt the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Let vs heare Doctor <hi>Couarrubias,</hi> who will tell vs the <hi>Etimology</hi> of <hi>Nominas,</hi> and withall confirme that which wee would proue. They were wont auntiently to carry purſes ſhut, and in them certaine writings and names of Saints, and ſo long as there was no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption nor ſuperſtition mixt, they were commonly the Goſpels of the foure Euangeliſts, and the names of Saints from whence they were ſtyled <hi>Nominas,</hi> and this was very lawfull and religious, but ſince they did annexe many other Apocriphall prayers, which they ſo intituled, that hee which hanged them about his necke, ſhould not dye by fire, water, nor by ſword, nor by ſentence of Iuſtice, and that the houre of his death ſhould be reuealed vnto him. Others haue foyſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid <hi>Nominas</hi> a hundred fopperies, which haue neyther head nor foot; he proues it by this example: One of theſe mockers gaue a <hi>Nomina</hi> vnto an Hoſtis which was ready to be brought to bed, affirming that ſhe ſhould bee well and ſafely deliuered; they made
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18960:8"/>him ſup well, and gaue Prouender to his Mule, and on the morning he tooke his iourney; they through cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie deſirous to ſee what was written within, found a ſchedule to this purpoſe, <hi>Coma mi mula, y cene yo, ſi quiera, para, ſi quiera no:</hi> that is, let my Mule feede, and me ſup, I care not whether ſhee bee deliuered or no: It is not remote from my intent to inſert here a famous fiction and deceit, by which a proflygate villaine cauſed for many ages diuers to weepe, and not a few to laugh; he cloathed himſelfe in a very ragged garment which he had ſtollen from an Hermit, &amp; put about his necke, a roſarie of Beades as big as Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, that the greatneſſe of them might make them more viſible and occular vnto all; (in him is verified the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> prouerbe, <hi>El roſorio al cuello, Y el diable en el cuerpo,</hi> which ſaith) Beades about the necke, and the Diuel in the body;) he girt about him a maſſy chaine of yron, his ſtockins and ſhooes were ſuch as hee brought with him into the world, that he might bee reputed not onely for a Fryer, but for a bare-footed Fryer; he ſhau'd off his beard, peraduenture to make a bruſh to ſprinckle holy water when hee was in his Hermitage: in concluſion, he ſo diſguiſed himſelfe, that his owne mother could not know him, though ſhe had viewed him with as many eyes as <hi>Argos</hi> had, they which ſaw him, were ſo farre from taking him for what he was, that they held him another Saint <hi>Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> or one of the Celebrious penitent Hermits, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the papiſticall Legends: So this holy and bleſſed Hermit, faſtening his eyes on the earth, as if he were ſeeking of pins, began, <hi>Con paſſos de frayle combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dado,</hi> to goe as faſt as a Fryer inuited to dinner
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18960:9"/>towards the Prouince of <hi>Biskaye,</hi> reſoluing to ſeat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a City of it, called <hi>Durango:</hi> He made choyſe of this City and Prouince, as iudging the people of <hi>Biskaye,</hi> the moſt ſimple and ignorant of any other in Europe, that ſo hee might with facility make ſale of his Phariſaicall hypocriſie, inſtead of Apoſtolicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and his iugling trickes in ſtead of admirable won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: He came to <hi>Durante</hi> in an vnhappy &amp; diſaſtrous houre, for thoſe of <hi>Durante</hi> who entertained him, and lodged him with ſuch ſingleneſſe, humanity, and courteſie as was worthy of that noble nation, being thereunto obliged by his penitentiall habit, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and ſanctimony which they ſaw in his outward actions, the opinion they conceiued of him was ſuch, that they publiquely honoured him as a bleſſed Saint, and ſaid, that God had ſent him vntothem, that by his good example and religious conuerſation, hee might rectifie their lines, and reforme their manners: They aſſigned him an Hermitage not farre from the City, that he might more conueniently deuote himſelfe to his heremetical exerciſes; the ſimple women began to viſit him in his Hermitage, euery one ſtriuing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her ability to carry him ſome thing to ſupply his want, and mittigate his pouerty: finally, in a ſhort time, this cunning Impoſter could ſo inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate himſelfe into theſe ignorant women, that hee thought hee could perſwade them to doe what hee would, ſuch was their ſimplicity; and ſeeing that hee had no neede of riches, becauſe the gifts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents which they made him, for adorning of an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Virgin which he had in his Hermitage, would plenteouſly ſuffice him all his life time, hee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18960:9"/>determined to lay hold on the occaſion offered vnto him, cauſing theſe women to change that holy and ſpirituall affection they bare him, into a flagitious and carnall one; He made no long delay to execute his purpoſe, for the day after, he began as well in the conferences which he held in his Hermitage, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which he vſed among the people, to publiſh as a thing knowne by reuelation, authentique, expreſſe, true, and communicated by the ſpirit of God, that the precept of brotherly charity required, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt neighbours, euen women ſhould be common, and perſwaded this as a truth, and ſo he finally enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his damnable and filthy deſire, vntill his deceit was manifeſted, and ſo he was forced to betake him to his heeles, and to relinquiſh his habite for being diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; hence grew the Prouerbe of <hi>la charidad de Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rango,</hi> the charity of <hi>Durango,</hi> vſed when a woman proſtituteth her body and honor; and becauſe he was call <hi>Alonſo,</hi> they ſo deadly hated this name, that though it be a very common name in <hi>Spaine;</hi> not any one in the City is ſo called, &amp; if any ſtranger ſo called, repaire thither, he changeth his name, which if he did not, they would ſtone him to death. For my part, I neuer was in that City, but I teſtifie before God, that I haue heard diuers Fryars of my Order, which liued there in a Monaſtery, to auerre all this for a truth, whereof the common Prouerbe formerly mentioned and vſed throughout all <hi>Spaine,</hi> is an euident argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>He that would be further informed concerning the Miracles fained by Fryars, let him ſee the bookes quoted in the Margents, the Author of the firſt being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18960:10"/>a Dominican,<note place="margin">Hiſtoria de la ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grada Orden de preaicaderes en los remotos Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos de la Eliopia</note> pretendeth to proue, and that by no few Writers, as alſo by eye-witneſſes, that in <hi>Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> there are many Monaſteries of his Order, and that the Fryars of them doe daily worke great Miracles. The Author of the ſecond booke being a Ieſuite,<note place="margin">Hiſtoria Y Anal relacion de la sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas que hizieron los padres de la compa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tia de Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, por las partes de Oriente, &amp;c.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an expreſſe Tractate, in which he euidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrateth, and by many occular witneſſes, that whatſoeuer the Dominican ſaith, is meerely falſe; and that the Fryars which hee ſaith are of his Order, are notable Heretickes, and that their Miracles, in caſe they be deuoyd of true faith, are eluſions of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to perſwade them that they haue the true faith, &amp;c. And hence we may conceiue what credit is to be giuen to Papiſticall Miracles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond ſort of Papiſticall Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, comprehendeth counterfeit or humane ſignes which were ſeene to happen, but were not true Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, though they ſeemed to be ſuch to the ſpectators.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch are the Miracles recited euer-and-anone in the Papiſticall Legends con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Images that ſweate bloud, whoſe haire and nailes grow, the which almoſt all the common people, and many others of better ranke, beleeue really to happen in ſome of our <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Images: but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18960:10"/>the truth is, that Fryars to attract the people and the almes of ſuch as giue credit to them, to their Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, doe faſten counterfeit haire to ſome Images of Chriſt crucified, and apply falſe nayles alſo, the which ſometimes they take away by night, placing in their roome others differing from them; and by ſuch ſlight (for herein they are dextrious Artifts) they perſwade the ignorant and ſimple people, that the haires and nayles doe truely grow, and with ſemblable iuglings they counterfeit the ſweating of Images: but let vs heare a learned perſon of <hi>Spaine</hi> what hee ſaith, and thinketh of ſuch Miracles and the actors of them; <hi>You muſt not credit,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Mateo Aleman en la hiſtoria de ſan Antoniode Padua pag. <hi>107.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>what ignorant and vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men affirme,</hi> ſaying, <hi>there are Images that ſweat bloud, whoſe haires waxe, and nailes are cut, it is an vntruth, a meere inuention and knauery:</hi> hee addeth, an Image of wood, or other mettall, cannot euacuate ſweat, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it's haire grow, for it is counterfeit, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the nayles which are carued by the hands of a wretched man, and in liueleſſe wood: The nailes (obſerue this) which truely grow, are the infernall auarice of thoſe who inuent them for their abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ends: theſe and ſuch like ſtratagems, acquire to the Fryars immunerable riches, to which no Indies but thoſe of Purgatory, which are the <hi>non vltra,</hi> are comparable. There are Images which maintaine very opulently a great multitude of Fryars; becauſe vpon the bruite of Miracles, infinite people reſort to them with money in their hands, for the ſight of ſuch Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is prohibited to ſuch as buy it not: Of which number is our Lady of <hi>Atocha,</hi> of <hi>Monſarrate,</hi> of <hi>Puy,</hi> the holy Crucifixe of <hi>Burgos;</hi> All theſe are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18960:11"/>houſes which from a mean beginning are by reaſon of the Images grown to ſo an incredible greatneſſe, that now they are the richeſt and moſt ſplended in all Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope. That of <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> is of my Order of the <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> of which I can report as an eye-witneſſe, that it may enter into competicion for riches with a City. When I was there, I diligently laboured to ſee ſome Miracle of thoſe infinite ones which the Fryars diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged daily of that Image, but I could neuer ſee any, and it happened alike to many of my Companions, and therefore one of them was wont to ſay, that the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of that Image were as thefts, which for the moſt part are done by night in the darke.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond ſort of Miracles,<note place="margin">Salazar en la hiſto. de la pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincia de Caſtilla de ſan Franciſco, pag. <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note> appertaineth that which ſome others relate of a certaine religious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which in <hi>Bolonia</hi> was held for a Saint, and ſhewed the wounds of the holy paſſion of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in her feete, hands, and ſide, and many times the bloud diſtilled from her head, as if it had beene pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with a crowne of thornes; and in fine, it was all found to be impoſture and couſenage: Of this I could alleadge many Hiſtories, as this Author acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but for auoiding prolixitie I omit them, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelfe with one moſt true preſident, which not many yeares ſince happened in <hi>Spaine.</hi> There was in <hi>Valladolid,</hi> a famous City of <hi>Spaine,</hi> a Ieſuite, who was ſo in loue with a noble Widdow which was wont to confeſſe vnto him, that perceiuing by her confeſſion, that ſhee was an impregnable caſtle, as being moſt chaſte, and fearing God, reſolued to conquer her by an extraordinary and miraculous way, to which intent, he ſuborned with many gifts, one of the ſaid Ladies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18960:11"/>Gentlewomen, that with all ſecrecy, ſhee ſhould put vpon, or neere the Boulſter of the Bed where ſhee ſlept, a little ſchedule, the which ſhe accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and her Miſtreſſe going to bed, found it, and much meruailing at it, called her Seruant, and asked her if ſhee had laid the ſchedule there; ſhee anſwered no, aſſeuering it with a thouſand oathes and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; this (and becauſe her Lady reputed her for an honeſt vertuous maide) cauſed her to thinke that ſhee knew nothing of the writing, &amp; becauſe there was no body elſe in the houſe, ſhe was perſwaded that it was ſent from heauen: ſhe remaining alone in her lodging, hauing firſt charged the Damoſell touching this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and reading the ſchedule, found the contents of it as followeth: <hi>Moſt deare Daughter, I haue elected you, that in this deplorable time, you ſhould be the Mother of a Sonne, that ſhall reforme the world, and this muſt happen by the co-operation of a man, chooſe whom you will, but marry not, for my will is that thou remaine a widdow.</hi> If the reading of this ſchedule bred admiration in her, it is needeleſſe to coniecture, it is ſufficient to tell you, that preſently after breake of day, ſhee went to ſeeke her Confeſſor, to whom ſhe declared <hi>ſub ſigillo confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis,</hi> what had befallen her the former night, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to counſell her what he thought beſt; hee perſwaded her after large conferences, (note the great ſubtilty of the Ieſuite) ſhe ſhould not lightly beleeue it, becauſe Sathan is wont to transfigure himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angell of light, to delude the better ſort, and that ſhe ſhould recommend that buſineſſe heartily to our Lady, and that hee would alſo doe it, that ſhee might inſpire what ſhould be beſt: and thus the Lady
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18960:12"/>returned to her houſe, and ſpent the greateſt part of the day in recommending vnto God the good ſucceſſe of it, and when night approached, ſhe entred into her chamber to lye downe, where ſhee found a ſecond ſcedule to the ſame purpoſe; preſently the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhe returned vnto her Confeſſor, who perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to tarry yet another night, and if ſhe found a third, then ſhe might hold it as a thing ordained by heauen, and ſhould diſpoſe her ſelfe to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of it; ſhe found one the next night conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither by the meanes aboue ſpecified, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating it vnto the Ieſuite, both of them determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with his no ſmall delight to beginne the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which was contained in the ſchedule, which was ennacted the ſame day in the houſe of the ſaid Lady, and continued ſome dayes, with the great ſhame and diſgrace of the Lady, and with ſuch impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and perpetude of the Ieſuite, that ſhe thought it paſt the bounds, not onely of a deuout and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man, but of the moſt carnall and brutiſh one in the world, ſhe began to ſuſpect that this Companion had beene the Author of the Miracle, which ſurmize increaſed, becauſe after ſhe had told him that ſhe was with childe, and that therefore no further action was needfull, in as much as when the end aimed at is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained vnto, the media conducing thereunto ceaſe; he notwithſtanding ceaſed not to importune her, and alſo to force her with ſmal modeſty to doe that which ſhe would haue excuſed: Theſe and other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, moued her to tell the Ieſuite, that becauſe her neighbours began to murmure and iudge ill of his frequent viſiting her, it was meete hee ſhould totally
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18960:12"/>forbeare her company; of neceſſity hee was faine to yeeld though vnwillingly: When her time of childe-bearing was come, ſhe had a faire Daughter, and ſo perceiued that the Ieſuite had beguiled her, ſhee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her kindred with the buſineſſe, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the diligence they vſed, could not deterre the malifactor who was fled away.</p>
               <p>There is no other which I know hath written this Hiſtory, but the common fame of it in <hi>Spaine</hi> implyes the truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the laſt kinde appertaine Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Miracles, which were onely iugling trickes, or did really happen: to this we referre caſting out of Diuels, healing of the ſicke, giuing ſight to the blinde, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which Father <hi>Ojea</hi> ſaith of the Miracles of <hi>Veſpatian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ojea en la vida de Chriſto pag. <hi>154.</hi>
                  </note> who reſtored ſight vnto a blinde man, and healed a lame man, his words are: The diuell could mingle with the ſpittle of <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> ſome powders of particular vertue which might forthwith take away the clowdes, and diſperſe the other obſticles which were in the eyes of the blinde man, that he might recouer his ſight; and when hee touched with his foote the other which was lame, hee might apply another remedy of thoſe many which are extant in nature, which he knoweth well
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18960:13"/>through his long experience, and ſo hee might bee healed. We iudge the ſame of Papiſticall Miracles: It cannot be denied but diuers meruailous effects haue bin produced among them, but either by deceit or art of the diuell, ſomtimes the Fryars themſelues not knowing it, &amp; ſomtimes holding correſpondency with the diuell: That this is ſo, the reaſons following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I. Becauſe Papiſticall Miracles are to corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſuperſtition &amp; falſe Doctrine, &amp; therefore cannot be eſſentially diuine; but that they confirme falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I proue by this inſuing example;<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> pag <hi>56.</hi> del prado eſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</note> the firſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is of an Abbot which abſolued a Fryar after he was dead, and impoſed a puniſhment vpon him that he ſhould be in Purgatory vntil his body were buried, as ſoon as the deceaſed heard this, he gaue a great &amp; fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhoute, which was heard all ouer the Moneſtary, ſaying, Oh mercileſſe Father, why haue you inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to abide ſo long in Purgatory? This example containeth, firſt, three, and thoſe no ſmall errors of the Romiſh Church; to wit, the doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, that of humane ſatisfaction, and the neceſſity of auricular confeſſion, and infoldeth alſo another er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror not onely repugnant to truth, but alſo contrary to that which the very Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues; to wit, that a man may be abſolued from his ſinnes after he is dead: And here I would intreate the firſt Monke that readeth this, to tell mee where that Fryar which departed was, vntill his Abbot came to giue him abſolution; for I cannot conceiue where he might ſoiourne during that intervall; for in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory hee could not be, whether (if we giue credence vnto Papiſts) none entreth vntill hee hath receiued
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18960:13"/>abſolution of his ſinnes, neither by the ſame reaſon could he be in heauen, becauſe the Papiſts doe not ſend the ſoules that haue beene in heauen vnto Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; but contrarily,<note place="margin">Nunnes can neuer come out of the Mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtary.</note> they ſend thoſe that are in Purgatory vnto heauen. As little could it be in hell; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as ſchoole-boyes know, there is no redemption; &amp; therfore the Prieſts ſaith not, <hi>deliuer vs Lord, ab infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> from hel, but, <hi>a porta inferi,</hi> from hel gate, and if once thou entreſt there, thou maieſt make ful account to be a Nunne of hel: wel, if this Fryar was neither in heauen, Purgatory, nor in Hell, where was he? alas I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got Limbus, but it is all one, for what had Limbus (a place deſtinate to Innocents) to doe with this nocent Fryar, which forgaue not his owne Abbot, euen then when hee dealt ſo compaſſionately with him? The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond example is of a Gentleman, who hauing vowed to turne Monke, was condemned for not being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in his vow, (though at the houre of his death,<note place="margin">Jbid pag. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> he vſed all the diligence which a good &amp; faithful Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an might vſe for acquitting of his conſcience: After his deceaſe hee appeared vnto an Abbot, which asked him; What doth the bleſſed Saint <hi>Vincent</hi> for thee, perchance he doth not aſſiſt thee in this thy neceſſity, ſeeing thou haſt giuen ſo much money to his Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators, that they might labour in building of his Moneſtary; to whom the Gentleman anſwered, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to him, but he hath made me wait many dayes to talk with him, &amp; when I could not doe it after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tedious attendances, I now deſpaire of euer talking with him, or hauing his fauour; it were friuolous to employ any arguments to perſwade the learned, or thoſe which are not altogether ignorant and blinde,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18960:14"/>that this is one of the moſt vaine Monaſticall fables, or ridiculous eluſions of Sathan; I ſay, for ſatisfaction of the ignorant, that this example hath for end and ſcope, the authorizing of one of the moſt pernitious errors of the Church of <hi>Rome, (viz)</hi> that the vow of leading a Monaſticall life, is not onely lawfull, but alſo that hee which performeth it not, can by no meanes be ſaued, how ſolicitous ſoeuer hee be for clearing of his conſcience. I would haue the Papiſts tell me, if thoſe dayes, which were not a few if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Papiſts, that Saint <hi>Vincent</hi> cauſed this poore Gentleman to dance attendance, preceded his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation yea or no; for if they did precede, then is it indubitorily falſe, that euery one heareth at his death the ſentence of his condemnation or ſaluation, which I preſume no papiſt in the world is ſo impudent as to affirme: if they were ſubſequent vnto his condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it followes that thoſe which are condemned in hell, come forth to ſolicite the Saints of heauen to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchize them from thence, and haue hope of their enlargement, &amp; that God wil revoke the ſentence he pronounced againſt them; for no man ſoliciteth a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, knowing it impoſſible to compaſſe his intent, all which how erronious, abſurd, and ridiculous it is let the Pontificies themſelues iudge.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place I ranke the reuelations made vnto many hee and ſhee Papiſticall Saints,<note place="margin">Soſa en al trata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do de la concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion Pag. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> eſpecially to Saint <hi>Bridget,</hi> to confirme the conception of the holy Virgin to haue beene without originall ſinne, which haue beene examined and allowed of as diuine ones, by many Cardinals and Prelates; yea, euen by the very Popes themſelues; whether theſe reuelations be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18960:14"/>reluctous vnto holy Scripture yea or no, I appeale to the iudgement of the famous and celebrious Order of Preaching Fryars, ſo called by way of eminency; the which with many others that ſimpathize with them herein, haue euidenced in their writings and Pulpits with luculent authoritie ſcited out of holy Writ and auncient Doctors, and with euident arguments, that the holy Virgin was conceiued in ſinne; and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this graue order of Dominicans is of ſuch force, that although the Pope complying with the Franciſcan and Ieſuiticall Orders, great <hi>Antagonis</hi> to the former, doth ratifie the ſaid reuelations, yet dares he not define this queſtion of the conception againſt them, though it be true, that according to the tenent of Papiſticall doctrine, he being in conſcience obliged to doe it, as many Pontificiall Doctors doe clearely demonſtrate, and amongſt them moſt elegantly, that renowned <hi>Soſa,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Segouia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vbi ſup.</note> I will tranſitorily ſay, that Cardinall <hi>Caietane,</hi> a conſpicuous Author, as all know, doth many Authors affirme, that Saint <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telyn</hi> haue a reuelation contradictory to that of Saint <hi>Bridget,</hi> which the Franciſcans and Ieſuites ſay; hee inuented of his owne head, to ratifye his opinion, whence appeareth, how the Fryars deride one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning the reuelations.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon prouing the Papiſticall Miracles to be diabolicall, is, becauſe the actions which they vſually alleadge for Miracles, are often times ſo chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh and ridiculous, that euery one may with facility perceiue that they proceede not from the holy Ghoſt;<note place="margin">Enel prado, eſpiritual pag. <hi>100.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch was that Miracle of the Crow, which for hauing ſtollen a Ring, as they ſay, did incurre ſentence of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18960:15"/>excommunication, and began forthwith to pine away by little and little, refuſing to eate, or crake, nor to continue the other paſtimes and demonſtrations of iockondneſſe, which irrationall creatures are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to doe, vntill an Abbot had abſolued it, from which moment the Crow began to bee iouiall, returning vnto it's former habit.<note place="margin">Ibid pag <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> Semblable vnto this Miracle, is that of a little Bitch, which dyed becauſe it entred into the holy Cell of Saint <hi>Gregory;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid pag. <hi>103.</hi>
                  </note> of like quality is that of Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> of whom it goes for current, that he excommunicated a great number of Flyes, which dyed, being ſtrucken with the arrow of excommunication: but aboue all theſe Miracles, that of a Fryar is remarkeable,<note place="margin">Ibid. pag <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> who kept the Swine of his combent, and on a day aſſembling them into one place, made vnto them this, no leſſe graue then elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent oration: you know brothers, ſwine, how in the time that I haue ſo carefully kept you, I haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently taught and inſtructed you, where you may, and where you may not feede; therefore I requeſt you, that you roue not out of your bounds, for feare of cauſing iarres in the Monaſtery, through the detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their neighbours; and in confidence that ſo you will doe, I will repaire to the Conuent, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you ſoone to returne: and ſo he went, and all the ſwine as if they had the vſe of reaſon, kept themſelues in the hils apertayning to the Fryars, inſomuch that ſome labouring men which deſired to catch them, could by no meanes driue them thence, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they gaue them many a blow with cudgels; who is there of ſound iudgement, that doth thinke God is the Author of ſuch fopperyes? It is the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18960:15"/>property of the diuell, and not of God, to delude men with ſuch.</p>
               <p>I will put a period vnto this diſcourſe, with one ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true and domeſticall example, that all the world may plainely diſcry the falſity of Papiſticall Miracles, and ſo abhorre them. A Dominican Nunne, called <hi>Mary of the viſitation,</hi> Prioreſſe of the Monaſtery of the Anunciada in <hi>Lisboa</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> furniſheth vs with this example, whoſe hypocriſie and forged Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles were diſcouered and condemned publiquely; diuers haue written of this holy Nunne, but a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nican Fryar called <hi>Eſteuan</hi> of <hi>Luſignan,</hi> hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely treated of her, collecting whatſoeuer he could finde to magnifie her, &amp; compiled a booke in <hi>French,</hi> which hee dedicated to the Queene of <hi>France,</hi> and cauſed it to be printed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>Iohn Beſſaut,</hi> in the yeare 1586. the title whereof is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great Miracles and moſt holy wounds which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Reuerend Matron for this preſent yeare</hi> 1586. <hi>Prioreſſe of the Monaſtery of</hi> Anunciada, <hi>in the City of</hi> Lisboa <hi>in</hi> Portugall, <hi>of the Order of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Fryars, approued of by the Reuerend Father</hi> Lewis de Granada, <hi>and other credible perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not here recite all which the Author alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but onely abreuiate what he ſaith in his Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Epiſtle as followeth.</p>
               <p>I hauing found ſome Writings printed in diuers Cities, haue gathered them together, in which inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiewing the greateſt Miracles and effects which in our age the omnipotent Lord hath wrought by a noble, vertuous, and religious Virgin, called as formerly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18960:16"/>moſt deuoted vnto the holy Sacrament, and of Saint <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> by whoſe merits and interceſſions ſhe hath deſerued to haue viſibly for her ſpouſe, Ieſus Chriſt crucified, and his fiue moſt ſacred wounds, by meanes whereof the diuine Maieſty continually wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked diuers Miracles.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Luſignan</hi> to countenance that which he ſaith, produceth three Letters, the firſt written by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall, <hi>Anthonio de la Cerda,</hi> &amp; ſent to <hi>Fernando Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> Procurer in <hi>Rome</hi> for the ſaid Prouince of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> that he might ſhew it to the Pope; the date of it is, from <hi>Lisboa</hi> the 14. of <hi>March</hi> 1584. The purport of the letter is, The Matron <hi>Maria de la viſitacion,</hi> being eleauen yeares old, betooke her ſelfe to a Nunnery, and when ſhe was of the age of ſixteene yeares, our Lord appeared occularly to this religious woman, to recompence her merits, and took her for his Bride, and ſince that time continueth alwaies to appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, granting her many particular fauours, talking familiarly with her, as one friend doth with another, after the ſame manner that God conferred with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and oft times manifeſted himſelfe to her, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſhee and hee Saints, and helped her to pray her canonicall prayers, and at the end of euery Pſalme, ſhee ſaid, <hi>gloria patri, &amp; tibi, &amp; ſpiritui ſancto,</hi> that is, glory be to the Father, and to you, and to the holy Ghoſt. In the ninth page he ſaith, when ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Communion, the other Nunnes percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her to be rauiſhed in ſpirituall extaſie a long while, vntill her ſuperior commanded her to goe to the Communion with the other Nunnes. In the elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth page he ſaith, ſo often as in the Nunnery ſhee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18960:16"/>heard the bell that accompanied the holy Corps of our Sauiour carried through the ſtreetes to the ſicke, ſhe kneeled on the ground with teares, and was exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically tranſported, as the Nunnes of the ſaid Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry teſtifieth: He further ſaith, that two ſeuerall times, a Cheſt wherein the Sacrament was, did open of it owne accord, and the Euchariſt lept out of it into her mouth: Further, in the 12. page, when ſhee was at prayers in her Cell, the Nunnes ſaw her inuironed with are ſplendency, and lifted vp into the aire, great brightneſſe ſtreaming from her breaſt and face, which ſignified the great and feruent charity and loue of God which is in her: One day Ieſus Chriſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto her, full of ſplendor, and crucified with his fiue holy wounds; out of his feete, hands, and ſide, he ſhewed beames of fire, which darted vpon the hands, feete, and ſide of this holy Nunne; the wounds and markes remained in her very beautifully, of ſanguine colour, as well on the in-ſide as the out-ſide of the palmes of her hands, and of her feete correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the one to the other, and being of a round fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure as of a nayle.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Letter was written by <hi>Lewis de Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> to the Patriarch of <hi>Valencia,</hi> wherein amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things he ſaith, as followeth. <hi>The Prioreſſe hath told me, that ſince ſeauen yeares, ſhe feeleth in her head, all the paines of the crowne of thornes, in ſuch extremity, that the bloud guſheth out, and ſhe hath in her head, ſmall holes and paſſages made by the ſaid thornes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Letter was written by the ſame Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, <hi>Antonio de la Cerda</hi> vnto <hi>Fernando Caſtro,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curor in <hi>Rome</hi> for the Prouince of <hi>Portugall,</hi> therein
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18960:17"/>he thus ſaith; <hi>Since your Reuerence departed out of this City, it hath pleaſed our Lord to ſhew from day to day, how acceptable vnto him the Prioreſſe of</hi> Annunciada <hi>is, for infinite are the Miracles, as well corporall as ſpirituall, which he doth by meanes of her in theſe parts, which haue cauſed very many Gentlemen to turne Fryars;</hi> anone hee ſaith, <hi>that three Mores inſpired by God, went to ſee her, as ſoone as they had ſeene her, they fell proſtrate to the ground on their faces:</hi> the manner of it was ſuch, that ſome of thoſe that were there preſent, were faine to helpe them vp; being vp, and looking on her the ſecond time, they kneeled downe, without ſaying any word, lamenting inceſſantly for a long time; their eyes being fixed on the Pryoreſſe, when I asked them wherefore they ſpake not to her, they anſwered, that they ſaw in her ſuch admirable things, that they knew not what to ſay; and then they intreated the Pryoreſſe that he that was by her might Baptize them; ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that I ſhould Baptize them; whereof I aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized the Archbiſhop, accompanying them vnto him with ſome other Fathers. They confeſt to him in our preſence, that they had ſeene by the Pryoreſſe, Ieſus Chriſt in humane ſhape faſtened on the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>Preſently hee mentioneth another Miracle, of a Dame that put vpon her lippes which were poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a little piece of linnen of the ſame Nunnes, and preſently ſhe was well. He addes another Miracle, of a woman that drinking water, into which had beene caſt two pieces of a Croſſe which this Prioreſſe had giuen her, ſhee was forthwith healed of her infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; and addeth, that the two pieces ioyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together in the water, &amp; made a perfect Croſſe.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18960:17"/>
               <p>All this is gathered out of the afore-mentioned booke, the fame of the holineſſe of this Nunne was ſo renowned, that Cardinall <hi>Albertus</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſent an information of it to Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the ſift, to whom the Pope writ this enſuing Letter, <hi>Wee read with much contentation, the Letter which you cauſed to bee written vnto vs of the vertues of the Prioreſſe, and of the great bleſsings which God hath conferred vpon her; ſupplicating his diuine bountie to make her from day to day worthy of his grace, and inrich her with his Coeleſtiall gifts, to the glory of his name, and the comfort of his faithfull ones;</hi> Dated in <hi>Rome</hi> in Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> with the ſeale of the Fiſher, the 10. of <hi>September,</hi> 1584.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antonio Pruchae Badulmi</hi> vnder writ it.</p>
               <p>Now that we haue heard the <hi>pro,</hi> let vs heare the <hi>contra,</hi> the true Ieſus Chriſt, (and not the ſpouſe of this Nunne, which was the Diuell) was pleaſed to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske this bride of Ieſus Chriſt, reputed ſo holy and full of charity, &amp; an actreſſe of Miracles, and ſo to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt all her abhominations, ſuperſtitions, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and ſo at the end of the yeare, 1588. which was the Admirable yeare, ſhe was condemned, as a booke witneſſeth, printed in <hi>Ciuill</hi> at the beginning of the yeare 1589. following: out of which is taken word for word, what I will ſay againſt her; the title of it is, <hi>A relation of the ſanctity and wounds of</hi> Mary <hi>of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, which was Prioreſſe of the Annunciada of</hi> Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boa, <hi>and that which was declared in the ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt her.</hi> Diuers graue perſonages being deputed to examine the verity of her wounds, and ſanctimony, repaired to the Nunnery, and found by the teſtimony of many Nunnes vniformly agreeing,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18960:18"/>that the ſanctity of the Prioreſſe was counterfeited, and the wounds painted, notwithſtanding the Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe denied it, vntil they took hard ſope &amp; hot water, and waſht her hands throughly with them, and the wounds ouer them; during the which, ſhee faigned the feeling of great paine: in concluſion, when the wounds vaniſhed away, ſhe fell on the ground, and began to weepe, ſigh, and craue mercy; caſting her ſelfe at the Deputies feete, and being required to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth, ſhe ſaid that ſhee had painted theſe wounds on her hands, &amp; did it ordinarily, &amp; that that one on her ſide ſhe had onely did it thrice with a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife, and that the crowne of thornes on her head, ſhe had made it with pricking her ſelfe with a knife vntill the bloud followed, and that ſhe had done this ſixe or ſeauen times: being asked how ſhe had figured the fiue drops of bloud vpon thoſe little clouts which ſhe ſaid came from the wound of her ſide; ſhe reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſhe had cunningly painted ſome fine Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land cloath with bloud, and when they preſented her any peices of linnen to touch the wound ſhe fained to haue in her ſide, ſhee did cut them in the preſence of thoſe that gaue them her, ſhaping them according to the forme of thoſe ſhe carryed in her boſome, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the peices ſhe had receiued into her boſome, ſhee pluckt it out, &amp; gaue inſtead of them thoſe which ſhe had painted with bloud: Being demanded how ſherai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelfe vp, &amp; how the Nuns often times ſaw her glitter in her Cell; ſhee anſwered, that ſhee fiered a few coales in a Chafing-diſh, and did ſet it before a Looking-glaſſe, and the beames of it which were in the Looking-glaſſe, did reflect vpon her face; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18960:18"/>that ſhee might ſeeme to bee eleuated and lifted vp, ſhe did put her feete into a high kinde of ſhooes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chapines,</hi> and ſometimes vpon ſtilts, which ſhee had for that purpoſe; and was ſo dextriouſly placed vpon them, that ſhe ſeemed to bee in the aire. After theſe interrogatories, her faults being manifeſt, ſhee was condemned the 6. of <hi>December,</hi> 1588. in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtary of the mother of God of this City, and in her preſence was pronounced and read her ſentence: She was not condemned to be burned, but onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned certaine Monaſtical penances, becauſe the fury and rage of the Inquiſitors is onely ſatiated with the bloud of the truely faithfull, which they call <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> as alſo becauſe the Nunne was of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Order, of which Order moſt of the Inquiſitors are.</p>
               <p>About the yeare of our Lord 1540. there was in the City of <hi>Cordoua,</hi> another Nunne which was Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oreſſe of the Nunnery of Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> who was condemned by the Inquiſitors of the ſame City for enormous crimes and compacts which ſhe had made with the Diuell; by whoſe aſſiſtance ſhee did ſuch things, that throughout all <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhee was reputed and adored for a Saint: The Hiſtory of whom, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian de Valera</hi> truely recounteth in his tractate of the Maſſe.</p>
               <p>We may conclude from the premiſes, that ſeeing Miracles doe not alwaies accompany the true and Catholique Faith, and are common to the Miniſters of God, and thoſe of the diuell, of whom Scripture witneſſeth that he ſhall doe them, to deceiue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the faithfull; experience alſo teacheth vs, that he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18960:19"/>ſo doth;<note place="margin">Payua en ſus ſermones pag. <hi>261</hi>
                  </note> we cannot iudge by them of Religion, but rather contrarily (as ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> with whom Doctor <hi>Payua</hi> concurreth.) Examine and try Miracles by the pure and holy Doctrine of the Church, and obedience of the Law of God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto if they be punctually anſwerable, wee may hold them for true and diuine ones; if otherwiſe, for falſe and diabolicall, yea though they ſeeme to be the moſt prodigious Miracles that euer were ſeene; for what greater Miracles then thoſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles? And yet if the Phariſies could haue imputed vnto him or them the leaſt breach of Gods Law, they had liberty not to beleeue them; as the ſaid Doctor <hi>Payua</hi> proueth very learnedly,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and this is ſo pregnant a truth, that it cauſed <hi>Lactantius</hi> to ſay,<note place="margin">Torreſ. en ſu Philoſophia mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. pag. <hi>849.</hi>
                  </note> whom Doctor <hi>Torres</hi> alledgeth &amp; followeth, <hi>Non idcirco à nobis creditur Chriſtus, quia mirabilia fecit, ſed quia vidimus facta eſſe omnia quae nobis annunciata ſunt vaticinio Prophetarum,</hi> (that is) Chriſt is not therefore beleeued by vs becauſe he wrought Miracles, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee haue ſeene all things accompliſhed which were foretold vs by the Prophets. And the auntient Martyr <hi>Ignatius</hi> had the courage to ſay,<note place="margin">Jgnacius epiſt. ad Occeanum &amp; Pamach.</note> 
                  <hi>Euangelio ſe non crediturum, niſi videret in antiquis;</hi> that he would not giue credit to the Goſpell, vnleſſe he ſaw it in the Prophets, which is the ioynt voyce of all the Saints and Doctors of the Church, as the ſaid <hi>Torres</hi> notifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: but if it bee thus, as thus it is, why ſhould the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> preferre his Miracles before thoſe of Chriſts? willing that they ſhould be the rule of Faith, the others not hauing beene ſo? and why ſhould wee be ſo fooliſh as to vndervalue the auntient and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18960:19"/>aduiſe and directions, which doe place Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles after Doctrine, and follow the new and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaticall which doth preferthem? No, no, let vs not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelues to be ſo deluded, principally in matters of ſuch conſequence as this is; let vs cenſure Miracles by Doctrine, and not contrariwiſe Doctrine by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; and ſeeing Papiſticall Doctrine is farced with a thouſand ſuperſtitions and errors, let vs not indure to be ouercome by Miracles, eſpecially ſeeing they are (as hath beene copiouſly expreſſed) either coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit or fayned, or diabolicall. As often therefore as the Papiſts ſhall obiect them vnto vs, let vs ſtop their mouthes, ſaying with Saint. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate eccae.</note> 
                  <hi>Romoueantur iſta vel figmenta hominum mendacium, vel portenta Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituum fallacium, aut enim non ſunt vera quae dicuntur, aut ſi aliqua mira facta ſunt, magis cauere debemus: quod cum dixiſſet Dominus, quoſdam futuros eſſe fallaces, qui nonnulla ſigna faciendo, etiam electos ſi fieri poſſet, falle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent adjecit vehementer commendans &amp; ait: Ecce praedixi vobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs remoue thoſe fictions of lying men, or prodigies of deceitfull ſpirits, for eyther they are not true, which are reported, or if any Miracles haue beene done, we ought to be more cautious and wary, ſeeing our Lord hath ſaid, <hi>there ſhall come decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, which by doing of ſignes, ſhall deceiue euen the elect, if it were poſsible;</hi> hee addeth, emphatically, ſaying, <hi>Behold I haue foretold it you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
